Guide to the Truman A. Warner Papers MS 026
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series I, Research Files
  - Connecticut Towns
    - Ridgefield, 1948, 1971-1996 (Box 2, Folder 35-42)
      Articles on history and historical figures, Indian land and settlements, Georgetown, Keeler Tavern, land use and Master Development Plan, Casagmo mansion, Negro students, and Alabama segregation 1960, and Rochambeau/Revolution. Newspaper supplements. Research notes.
    - Ridgefield Chamber of Commerce Town Guide (map), 1974 (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Danbury Business #1 (20th Century)
    Business enterprises -- Connecticut -- Danbury; Consolidation and merger of corporations -- Connecticut; Corporate reorganizations -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- Economic conditions; Toy industry - United States; Retail trade - Connecticut; Industries -- Connecticut; Tourism -- Connecticut
    - Business Downsizing, 1994-1996 (Box 7, Folder 41-42)
      Effect of downsizing on individuals and local economy.
    - Business and Industry, 1935-1980 (Box 7, Folder 43)
      News articles dealing with growth and decline of local businesses, general economic overview of various area businesses including restaurants. Pamphlet dated 1971 outlines the growth of National Can Corporation.
    - Business and Industry, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 44)
      Growth/decline of area businesses, consolidation of businesses, job losses, counseling, economy, super-sized supermarkets, traffic, new construction, video stores, and service industries.
    - Business and Industry, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 45-47)
      Articles on rise and fall of several industries, opening of small restaurants, and the trend to large shopping malls. Some reference is made to employment trends, moving and finding employees, and the status of Connecticut income.
    - Business and Industry, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 48-49)
      Newspaper articles concentrate on the accelerated growth of Danbury in the 1980s.
    - Business and Industry, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 50-52)
      The construction/opening of the Mall in 1986, increases in office buildings, office parks, condominimum complexes, and housing developments.
    - Business and Industry, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 53-55)
      Failure of local businesses, trends in other local businesses, openings and closings of restaurants and some industries, regional economic forecasts, and Connecticut's place in national income.
    - Business and Industry, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
      Articles cover local businesses, openings and closings of industries, and regional economic forecasts.
    - Business and Industry, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
      Navy contracts, office vacancies, headhunters, layoffs and closing of industries, new construction, retail, traffic, entrepreneurs, and local economic conditions.
    - Business and Industry, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Focus on business in greater Danbury, corporate, retail, people and banking.
    - Business and Industry, 1992-1997 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      Focus on retail, Route 6 merchants, New Milford recycling plant, Nestle, TRC robots for elderly, Costco, and new construction.
    - Chamber of Commerce/Better Business Bureau, 1967-1984 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
      Articles contain change of personnel in Chamber of Commerce and accomplishments An objection to Sunday selling is noted in the Chamber of Commerce's Annual Report for 1971.
    - Better Business Bureau Magazine (newspaper supplement), 1978 (Box OS 3, Folder *)
    - Connecticut Business Review, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Corporate Growth Impact, 1970-1982 (Box 8, Folder 13-17)
      Personal research notes on political growth. Overview of the three part conference Danbury Corporate Influx. Also focus and analysis on corporate transferees, family relocation, and the attendant economic growth policies/problems/decisions confronting area school and local government. Research paper: Comparative and Value Conflicts by Joan Supp. 1977. Preliminary draft of Ellen Rosenberg's paper entitled Regional Culture and Politics of Growth, New England Ideology, New York Reality. 1978.
    - Corporate Structures, 1959-1996 (Box 8, Folder 18-20)
      Local businesses sold to, merged, or taken over by large corporations, loss of local control of media via de-regulation.
    - The Courant, Fourth Annual Edition, 1996 (Box OS 3, Folder *)
    - Danbury News-Times, City of Danbury Annual Report, 1969-1970, 1972 (Box OS 3, Folder *)
    - Danbury News-Times Business Supplements, 1972-1996 (Box OS 3, Folder *)
      27 supplements
    - Economics, 1987-1997 (Box 8, Folder 21-23)
      Emphasis on growth of new industry, job training, and pension problems, capital gains avoidance schemes by corporations, and disparity between the rich and the poor. The growth of malls and loss of independent shops absorbed by larger malls and mergers.
    - Industrial Development, 1750-1986 (Box 8, Folder 24-29)
      Articles and research notes on local changes in business, immigration, and naturalization. Student research paper: Danbury by Eileen Kelly, nd.
    - Industries 1950s-1960s, 1950-1969 (Box 8, Folder 30-33)
      Mergers and buy-outs of regional businesses.
    - Industries 1970s-1980s, 1970-1983 (Box 8, Folder 34-39)
    - Japanese in Danbury, 1983-1989 (Box 8, Folder 40)
      Several articles review the failure of Kero-sun products after Toyotomi refused to supply products. Pilot Pen, a Japanese subsidiary, bought a plant in Trumbull, and Mitsubishi acquired Digital Recording Company in Brookfield.
    - Mergers-Department Stores, 1975-1987 (Box 8, Folder 41)
      Robert Hall stores, Ohrbach's, Jordan Marsh, Macy's, Bloomingdale's, Campeau Corporation, and Federated Department Stores.
    - Pre-1940, 1926-1986 (Box 8, Folder 42-43)
      Articles of local people who invented, discovered or developed/founded a variety of tools and services. Booklets: Connecticut Tercentenary, 1635-1935, The Collins Company, 1935; Charles Goodyear and the Invention of Vulcanized Rubber, 1939; Connecticut Resources Bulletin No. 2, Manufacturing; New Haven Tercentenary Exposition, June 1938 Official Program, The Industrial Minuteman published under the auspices of the Foremen's Club of New Haven; and The Fulton Skyhook manufactured by the Robert Fulton Company (3-step rescue system).
    - SNET Market Report, Danbury-New Milford Area, 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 44-45)
      Contains the general economic picture of Danbury and area towns.
    - Tourism, 1976-1996 (Box 8, Folder 46-47)
      Development of tourism in the Danbury area, a formation of tourist districts, and pros and cons and solutions of tourism.
    - Toy Industry, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 48)
      Articles on Connecticut manufactured toys.
    - Transition 1940s-1960s, 1949-1969 (Box 8, Folder 49-53)
      Newsletters, digests, business indicators, decline of hat industry and rise of new industries, labor shortages, labor unions, and Interstate 84 See also: Student Research Papers #319: A Study of Danbury's Industrial Transition by Raymond J. Trimpert (1969)
  - Danbury Business #2 (20th Century)
    Danbury (Conn.) -- Flood, 1955.; Land use-Connecticut-Planning Newtown (Conn.); Water resources development -- Connecticut -- Planning; Water resources development -- Environmental aspects -- Connecticut; Hubbell Space Telescope; Water-supply -- Connecticut; Risdon Corporation; Danbury (Conn.); Perkin Elmer Corporation; Pesticides industry-India-Bhopal-Accidents; Flood control-Connecticut; Sherman (Conn.); Brookfield (Conn.); City planning; Roads-Connecticut; Connecticut Geology -- Soil Task Force; Floods-Connecticut; Urban renewal-Connecticut-Danbury; Urban renewal-Connecticut; Transportation-Connecticut-Planning; Bethel (Conn.); Union Carbide Plant Disaster; Medallic Art; Bhopal Union Carbide Plant Disaster, Bhopal, India, 1984
    - American Cyanamid - Davis and Geck, 1959-1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Local news on company growth and development, plant expansion, manufacture of sutures. Some articles on patent infringements and inventions.
    - Amphenol, 1958-1987 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Local news on company growth and development. Photo journal articles on the move into East Franklin Street plant vacated by Barden, and final closing and sale of company in 1986.
    - Bard-Parker, 1958-1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Brief news articles on history (1933), company downsizing and sale in 1976 to Aldrich Precision Manufacturing Company who manufacture surgical instruments.
    - Barden, 1957-1996 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
      Local news articles on company's activities such as new plant construction and plant sales. Good information on the development of the Norden WWII bombsight, ultra precision ball bearing assembling/manufacturing/aerospace and the partnership/friendship of Theodore Barth and Carl Norden, which produced the company name Barden. Information regarding the 1984 fraud case, 1988 economic difficulties, and involvement in a Norden investigation probe.
    - Berol/Eagle Pencil, 1958-1988 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Relocation of Eagle Pencil from New York to Danbury in 1958. Ribbon cutting ceremony and the development and changes at Berol.
    - Boehringer Ingelheim, 1974-1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      News and development of company from 1974 to 1997.
    - Branson Sonic Power, 1968-1992 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Brief local company news.
    - Data Communication and Data Control, 1957-1988 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Articles report on the development, growth and financial crisis of the company.
    - Doran, 1958-1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      One hundred eleven years of history. Original Lansden electric truck chassis developed in 1918. Moved to Bethel in 1985 by the Doran Brothers.
    - Duracell, 1984-1996 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      Company history, growth, development, downsizing, worker lay-off, and closure. Sold to management investment firm KKR for $1.8 Billion.
    - Ethan Allen, 1970-1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Relocation of company from New York to Danbury in 1970.
    - Garment Industry, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      One article on Grand Manufacturing Company, Shalvoy Lane. Last area shirt manufacturer.
    - Gilbert and Bennett, 1967-1996 (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
      History and development of the company in Georgetown and move to Georgia in 1989. Later articles deal with development plans, problems for the vacated site as Georgetown is now on the National Register.
    - Grolier, 1970-1995 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      Company established in Danbury in 1970. Articles deal with the growth and development of electronic publishing (encyclopedias), fiscal policies, a and buyout by Hachette in 1988.
    - Heli-Coil, 1970-1985 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      Very brief content.
    - IBM, 1969-1989 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      News articles cover corporate culture, and editorials/photos cover the move to Danbury, Southbury and Ridgebury.
    - Kimberly Clarke, 1957-1997 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      News articles.
    - Medallic Art-Danbury Mint, 1971-1989 (Box 9, Folder 20)
      Local growth, development, and closing of the company. Coverage of local ecological problems caused by the acid bath/etching process.
    - Novo Laboratories, 1983-1989 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      Pharmaceutical company in Ridgefield who produces industrial enzymes. News articles detail growth of company.
    - Perkin Elmer, 1959-1989 (Box 9, Folder 22-24)
      Articles on the growth of the company in Danbury from 1957.
    - Perkin Elmer/Hughes/Hubble, 1983-1997 (Box 9, Folder 25-29)
      News articles/editorials/opinions on the aftermath and effects on the local economy of the Hughes/Perkin Elmer defective telescope.
    - Pitney Bowes (Alpex), 1970-1994 (Box 9, Folder 30)
      Brief information on corporate news events, downsizing, and marketing strategies.
    - Reeves Soundcraft Corporation, 1957-1959 (Box 9, Folder 31)
      Brief articles.
    - Republic Foil, 1959-1984 (Box 9, Folder 32)
      Corporate news events and manufacturing problems.
    - Risdon Corporation - 1983-1990, undated (Box 9, Folder 33)
      Local corporate events. Articles focus on manufacturing problems-pollution controls in manufacture of lipsticks/cosmetics.
    - Scovill, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 34)
      Brief content.
    - Sperry Products, 1959-1982 (Box 9, Folder 35)
      Corporate news events.
    - Sperry Schlumberger, 1973-1987 (Box 9, Folder 36)
      Local corporate news and events. Booklet: Men and Mines dated 1973.
    - Union Carbide/Bhopal, 1983-1994 (Box 9, Folder 37-40)
      Bhopal Disaster from local and international global perspectives. The articles give an insight into local reactions and the effects on the local economy and company personnel.
    - Union Carbide/GAF, 1985-1987 (Box 9, Folder 41-42)
      This file deals with corporate events, mainly the attempted hostile takeover bid by GAF and the subsequent actions taken by Union Carbide to pay off the debt. This file is a source of information on how global corporate policies affect local economies and work force.
    - Union Carbide/Relocation, 1975-1990 (Box 9, Folder 43-47)
      Relocation of Union Carbide to Danbury in the 1970's and the subsequent impact on the area. Issues covered are business/economic incentives, relocation problems, land use, highway, and plant construction. Changing Patterns of Land Use in Danbury, Connecticut by Dr. H. Janick. January 16, 1981.
    - Unimation, Inc., 1966-1997 (Box 9, Folder 48-49)
      Entrepreneur/inventor Joseph Engleberger and the growth and development of his robotic business from 1966 to 1987.
  - Danbury Business & Economy
    See also: Student Research Papers #320: The Sources of National Economic Policy and its impact on the economy of the Danbury area, on Connecticut, and on the nation 1969-1970 by Paulette Pepin, 1971.
    Connecticut -- Economic conditions; Connecticut -- Economic policy; Economic development -- Connecticut; Economic history - Connecticut; Regional economics - Connecticut; United States - Economic policy
    - Bernardi, John L. The Current State of the Connecticut Economy, undated (Box 9, Folder 50)
      1982. Paper presented to: Tenth Annual Meeting of the New England Business and Economic Conference, November 1982, Springfield MA., by John L. Bernardi, Asst. Professor of Economics, WCSC.
    - Connecticut Economy, 1971-1996 (Box 9, Folder 51-52)
      Articles on economy, recession, and world trade.
    - Economic History, 1977-1995 (Box 9, Folder 53)
      Research notes and sources.
    - Economy, 1967-1976 (Box 9, Folder 54)
      General overview of Danbury and the Fairfield County economy. Most of the articles refer to residential/industrial conflicts, planning and zoning problems, corporate restructuring, job security and planning for long term growth.
    - Economy, 1977-1979 (Box 9, Folder 55)
      Articles focus on local businesses and editorials.
    - Economy, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 56-57)
      Articles cover the 1980 boom years and the growth of a service economy based on real estate, construction, corporate office parks, malls, and shopping plaza/centers.
    - Economy, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 58)
      Articles concern the end of the boom years, the State's 1990 deficit/downturn and job losses, downsizing, and corporate flight of companies from Connecticut.
    - Economy, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 59-62)
      Articles concern new employment trends, and the need to educate students at both high school and college level for a more technical, cyberspace/computer literate work force.
  - Danbury - Downtown Redevelopment
    See also: Danbury Preservation Trust
    Truman Warner Papers-Railways
    Truman Warner Papers-Floods
    Truman Warner Papers-Still River Watershed
    Land use -- Connecticut -- Danbury -- Planning.; Danbury (Conn.) -- History.; Still River (Conn.); Economic development projects - Connecticut - Danbury; P. W. Genovese & Associates; Flood control - Connecticut - Danbury; Technical Planning Associates; Danbury (Conn.) -- City Planning; Danbury (Conn.) -- Economic conditions
    - Redevelopment, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Articles on the establishment of a Redevelopment Agency under the Chairmanship of George F. O'Brien, flood controls, urban renewal for Liberty Street and environs plus the harnessing of the Still River. Lawrence Moore Technical Planning Associates estimated a projected area growth of 75% over 25 years and advised on parking, traffic patterns redevelopment and urban renewal projects.
    - Redevelopment, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Phase I of the redevelopment project includes highlights of the city plan under Mayor John Define, Jr., and Governor Ribicoff. Information on the city's application under Federal and State Grant programs. The key issues were flood control, redevelopment, consolidation and full time growth initiatives by city officials. Also, articles on Eagle Pencil, Hospital, Mill Ridge School, and St. Anthony's Maronite Church.
    - Plan of Development by the City of Danbury Planning Commission and Technical Planning Associates, August 1958. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Plan of Development by the City of Danbury Planning Commission and Technical Planning Associates, August 1958. (c.2) (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Redevelopment, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      City acts on renewal and flood control projects. Redevelopment plans show White, Elm, Main, Rose, Crosby, and Liberty Streets. Also, articles regarding local landmarks demolition projects.
    - Map: Street Map, City of Danbury with Central Flood Urban Renewal Project, 1959 (Box OS 3, Folder *)
      2 maps that appear to have been bound together, the street map of Danbury has annotations on it, the central flood urban renewal project map is a duplicate of the map in mapdrawer 8
    - Map: Central Flood Urban Renewal Project, Conn.R-30, Rev. 3/20/59., 1959 (Folder OS Folder 8, Item 6)
    - Danbury Redevelopment, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Research notes, articles/editorials on the redevelopment, relocation, and wrecking of defunct buildings. Phase II Urban Renewal Project, and plans for the redirection and relocation of the N.Y.N.H & H.R.R, Carney Street location. Blue Print for Danbury Future - Ten Point Plan: Articles/photos/editorials contain information and assessments of Danbury's future planning needs. Outlines of plans for land use, orderly development, establishment of a Planning Commission.
    - Plan of Development by the City of Danbury Planning Commission and Technical Planning Associates, July 1960. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Plan of Development by the City of Danbury Planning Commission and Technical Planning Associates, July 1960. (c.2) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Real Estate Appraisals by Robert N. Noce, SRA, January-April 1960 (Box 10, Folder 9-16)
    - Real Estate Appraisals by Karl G. Kaffenberger, Jr. M.A.I., January-March 1960 (Box 10, Folder 17-24)
    - Danbury Redevelopment, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 25)
      Published list of fourteen downtown properties to be demolished, the planned initial phase of the Still River flood control project, the projected parking and land acquisition under urban renewal, and demolition laws /statutes/ordinances.
    - Danbury Redevelopment, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 26)
      Phase II Urban Renewal Project. South White Street, Hoyt and Crosby Streets. Continuation of work on Yankee Expressway connector (I-84). Danbury High School move from White Street to Clapboard Ridge. Capital investment in redevelopment zone east of Main Street encouraged by city agencies
    - Redevelopment, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 27)
      Research notes and newspaper articles on Phase II of Urban Renewal Projects, relocation of the Still River, and establishment of the White Street bus terminal. Demolition projects on Elm, Rose, White, and Triangle Streets construction of Main Street Bridge.
    - Redevelopment, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 28-32)
      Articles on the demolition projects at Beaver Street, plans for railroad relocation, and Crosby Street Bridge before demolition. Central Flood Urban Renewal Project Conn. R-30, City Project No. 60-4C, by L. F. Sweeney, Inc., 1964
    - Redevelopment, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 33)
      Still River project, river containment and photos of the new bridge construction on Crosby Street, contracts for Elm Street divider, and plans for Danbury Shopping Plaza.
    - Redevelopment, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 34)
      Clippings on redevelopment and local economic problems affecting Danbury's struggle for downtown renewal. Editorial articles compare Danbury with the development projects of Torrington, Ansonia, and other neighboring towns.
    - Redevelopment, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 35-38)
      Redevelopment of the south side of the Still River, new stores, new parking lot at White Street, and a new City Hall proposal. HUD funds released to city and the introduction of the General Neighborhood Renewal Plan project - GNRP. Articles discuss planned development and the establishment of more stringent Plan of Development, June 1967 by Technical Planning Associates. land use regulations and building codes/zones. Also included land use studies.
    - Real Estate Appraisals by Robert N. Noce, SRA, Mid-town East Urban Renewal, undated (Box 10, Folder 39-46)
      Project R-104, November-December 1967, January 1968.
    - Redevelopment, 1968-1970 (Box 10, Folder 47-50)
      Projects at Main, White, Beaver and Crosby Streets, new Fire Department at New Street. Discussions on the need for a better cross town (east/west) route. Also included 1968 Central Flood Urban Renewal Project Conn. R-30, City Project No. 66-5 by P. W. Genovese & Assoc. (Construction of Crosby Street Bridge and Roadway and Padanaram Brook Channel for City of Danbury)
    - Redevelopment, 1971-1977 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
      Article/photos on projected stages of development. Patriot Drive, public works projects and expansion of sewer and water mains to bordering towns of Newtown and Bethel. Editorials on controversial growth into these rural areas particularly Federal Road--The Miracle Mile, and expansion on West Side--Mill Plain Road.
    - Redevelopment, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
      Danbury's future growth and impact on neighboring towns. 1979 is the pivotal year and the focus moves from downtown to the expansion of Mill Plain Road with the building of Union Carbide Corp Headquarters, the Hilton Hotel, and Westside WSCU campus.
    - State of Connecticut: Conservation Development Policies 1979-1982. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Redevelopment (Jerry Lombardi remarks), 1979-1983 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Information on the history of Danbury's redevelopment projects from the 1940's to 1980's. Copy of personal interview with Jerry Lombardi dated August 1, 1979, on the subject of Danbury redevelopment process.
    - Danbury - Planning for the 1980's, 1980-1989 (Box 11, Folder 8-12)
      Information on the challenge of area growth in the 1980s. The Danbury Renaissance discussed in a five-part lecture forum at WCSU in 1982 entitled The Problems of Growth by Johnathan Crew, Director of the Housatonic Council. Articles and editorial comments plus interviews with area selectmen focus on the effects to ecosystems and environment by unchallenged growth. It also reported on the comments of Dr. Truman A. Warner at the 1982 Forum. Parking Garage Plan 1986. See also: Floods, Still River Watershed, Railways
    - Revitalizing Downtown: A National Videoconference, September 18, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Downtown Danbury, 1985-1987 (Box 11, Folder 14-16)
      In depth articles/editorials/opinions on the plans for revitalizing downtown Danbury. Topics covered: Flood Control Project, mid-town east development project, downtown parking, Main Street parking, railway/train station, Danbury Preservation Trust, Ives Street/Firehouse, Patriot Drive, Liberty Street, 7 acre redevelopment parcel.